Albert W. Atwood 064 064
Stage
Albert W. Atwood Collection
1911-1975
Stage
064
11 linear feet; 8 boxes
Biographical / Historical
Albert W. Atwood was born in Jersey City, New Jersey in 1879. He graduated from Fredonia (NY) State Normal School in 1899 and from Amherst College in 1903. Albert W. Atwood was a leader in the scholarly, journalistic and philanthropic communities in Washington, DC in the early twentieth century. He served as President of the Board of Trustees for the DC Public Library, was President of the Cosmos Club, and was a regular contributor to The Saturday Evening Post and The National Geographic Magazine, as well as various local newspapers and journals. He also wrote a biography of Senator Francis G. Newlands and a history of Gallaudet College. He died in 1975 in Washington, DC.
Custodial History
The Albert W. Atwood Collection was accessioned into the DC Community Archives in 1998. The collection of materials was acquired by the DC Community Archives prior to 1998, but little information about the materials exists, save for a note in two of the volumes that read "Property of Mrs. Yates." The assumption is that Mr. Atwood created the materials, but this cannot be verified.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of scrapbooks containing Albert W. Atwood's articles and editorials from The Saturday Evening Post and The National Geographic Magazine, as well as three books and a poster from the DC Public Library. Also included are photographs, articles, and awards.
The control file for this collection contains a title index of Mr. Atwood's articles and editorials from The Saturday Evening Post.
Business; Libraries
- Series 1: General Documents
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of loose articles and addresses, photographs, awards, clippings, and biographical information.
  - Address: "Have You Read a Book?", March 20 1958 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Article: "The Soul of a City" The Saturday Evening Post, October 6 1928 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Article: "How Far Should Government Go?" The Saturday Evening Post, April 18 1931 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Article: "Where's the Money Coming From" The Saturday Evening Post, January 20 1934 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Article: "The Senate Investigates" The Saturday Evening Post, July 11 1936 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Article: "Everybody's Money" The Saturday Evening Post, December 26 1936 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Article: "Across the Potomac from Washington" The National Geographic Magazine - Vol. CIII no. 1, January 1953 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Biographical Information, Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Clippings, 1933-1975 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Invitation to Cleveland Park Branch Library Open House, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Memorial Service Programs, January 28 1975 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Photographs: Inspection Group-Chevy Chase Branch Library, December 4 1946 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Photographs: Open House-Cleveland Park Branch Library, October 15 1953 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Meritorious Public Service Award from the Government of the District of Columbia, September 23 1970 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Oversize Folder, Undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - The Hecht Co. Salutes the DC Public Library - advertisement, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Series 2: The Saturday Evening Post Scrapbooks
  This series contains seven scrapbooks of Mr. Atwood's work that appeared in The Saturday Evening Post. The items in each scrapbook are separated by articles and editorials. Some of the scrapbooks contain indexes.
  - Untitled, 1911-1915 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Untitled, 1914-1920 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Untitled, 1920-1922 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Untitled, 1923-1926 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Untitled, 1927-1931 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Untitled, 1931-1934 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Untitled, 1933-1936 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Meritorious Public Service Award from the Government of the District of Columbia, September 23, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Series 3: Bound Volumes
  This series consists of books written by Mr. Atwood, as well as, The National Geographic Magazine articles authored by Mr. Atwood.
  - Francis G. Newlands: A Builder of the Nation - The Newlands Company, 1969 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Gallaudet College: It's First One Hundred Years - Gallaudet College, 1964 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - The Great Stwedarship: A Story of Life Insurance - Harper and Brothers Publishers, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - "Washington—Storehouse of Knowledge" Vol. LXXXI no. 3, March 1942 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - "Tidewater Virginia - Where History Lives" Vol. LXXXI no. 5, May 1942 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - "The Miracle of War Production" Vol. LXXXII no. 6, December 1942 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - "The Long River of New England" Vol. LXXXIII no. 4, April 1943 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - "Revealing Earth's Mightiest Ocean" Vol. LXXXIV no. 3, September 1943 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - "The Healing Arts in Global War" Vol. LXXXIV no. 5, November 1943 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - "Coal: Prodigious Worker for Man" Vol. LXXXV no. 5, May 1944 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - "Potomac, July 1945 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - "Northeast of Boston" Vol. LXXXVIII no. 3, September 1945 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - "Steel: Master of Them All" Vol. XCI no. 4, April 1947 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - "Washington: Home of the Nation's Great" Vol. XCI no.6, June 1947 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - "The Mighty Hudson" Vol. XCIV no. 1, July 1948 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - "The Fire of Heaven—Electricity" Vol. XCIV no. 5, November 1948 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - "Pittsburgh: Workshop of the Titans" Vol. XCVI no. 1, July 1949 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - "Gilbert Grosvenor's Golden Jubilee" Vol. XCVI no. 2, August 1949 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - "The Nation's Library" Vol. XCVII no. 5, May 1950 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - "The Merrimack: River of Industry and Romance" Vol. XCIX no. 1, January 1951 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - "The Eternal Flame—Natural Gas" Vol. C no. 4, October 1951 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - "Today on the Delaware, July 1952 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - "Stately Homes of Old Virginia" Vol. CIII no. 6, June 1953 (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - "Immigrants Still Flock to Liberty's Land" Vol. CVIII no. 5, November 1955 (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - "1960 Census: Profile of the Nation" Vol. CXVI no. 5, November 1959 (Box 8, Folder 25)